this is just
a small section in the majima nikaya 77
and this is the 10 casinos
it says i have proclaimed to my
disciples the way to develop the ten
casinos one contemplates the earth casino above
one contemplates the earth casino above
below
across undivided and immeasurable
well that's it just do the first one
yeah and thereby many disciples of mine
abide having reached the perfection and
consummation of direct knowledge
so there's
literally means totality
that's the meaning of the world casino
um
and i think even in sanskrit it is the
same the totality the extent
something so it only occurs in
i think a couple of the sutas so i think
it was mostly like
later interpretations we kind of took on
the whole practice
and today when people hear casino they
think about
staring at the clay discs or balls
filled with water but even the wood
themselves says you contemplate
you develop you establish your mind upon
it so it's like
establishing your mind upon a certain
greater extent
the greater totality from the totality
that your mind dwells on to day to day
level which is pretty much totality of
which is pretty much totality of
sensuality totality of ill will
and so on so when we talk about
developing uh
discerning the greater context
peripherally and then maintaining that
in your mind through your own salty and
mindfulness not forgetting it that's already
not forgetting it that's already
practicing that establishing mine upon a
better totality
because totality means it unifies
whether you are
turning left right forward backward up
down doesn't matter which direction you take
doesn't matter which direction you take
it's all within certain totality
and that's why i'm broken immeasurable
i'm broken by your choices i'm broken by
your directions and so on
so if your mind is established like for
example in terms of the context that people can
in terms of the context that people can
relate to
establish your mind upon the context of
sense restraint
so it doesn't matter then if you want
the sensuality
if you don't want centrality if your
balance is training if you're
unsuccessful in your restraint
the value the totality of the value of
sense restraint
remains there held up by you so you
still have at least a chance
then to return to it and start well
and align your behavior correctly to
that to that totality of that value
the context the context exactly it's the
worst if you
abandon the totality of the value of
sense restraint
and then even if you don't necessarily
engage with sensuality you're not
valuing freedom from it and you will
thus you will never make sufficient
effort to free yourself from it
if you maintain that totality as
unbroken value
even if you neces like imperfect in your
sense restraint in the beginning
you can eventually perfect it because
the totality remains there as an anchor
point as a reference point
so that's when similarly in other suits
when the buddha said the monk who has
withdrawn from village from the crowd
lives in seclusion solitary life in the
forest his mind establishes himself upon the
his mind establishes himself upon the
perceptions of the forest
and he recognizes any perceptions they
will come on a kind of inferior village
life they would bother somebody cannot bother
they would bother somebody cannot bother
me because my mind is established upon
the perception of the forest that's
where i dwell
but if something were to happen to the
forest i would be disturbed
so if somebody comes and starts cutting
trees and destroying that forest
his perceptions would then go so then
his mind would not be established
because the totality is gone
so then he recognizes that liability so
then he reflects thus or what if i were to
he reflects thus or what if i were to
establish my mind upon even a greater
totality that cannot be destroyed easily
the totality of earth because earth is
the totality that's in common to the
forest and the village and in between
and the city
wherever you might be but the problem
for people
like is when you hear this it's just too
abstract to begin with oh the idea of
earth because that idea doesn't stand for
because that idea doesn't stand for
anything in their experience but that's
because their experience hasn't been
cultivated sufficiently enough
so that they can discern the element of
earth within their experience
and when i say cultivate sufficient
enough means unbroken sealer develops
efficiently enough sense restraint
dedicated to sufficient enough
mindfulness cultivate sufficient enough
right views developed sufficiently
enough otherwise it will be just an abstraction
otherwise it will be just an abstraction
that you will then sort of
mystify and fantasize and equate with
stating that a clay ball somehow
like would take your mind into the
magical dimension of the totality of
earth no you contemplate the extent of earth
no you contemplate the extent of earth
the extent of solid which is in common
to me
you village mountains everything
and it's there for you the the factual
the verticity of your body
if seen rightly reveals the element of
earth the great earth if seen rightly
the great earth if seen rightly
the the element of water the totality
not the actual physical
particular thing you focus on so all
these totalities
are on the level of peripheral and even
more peripheral if your mind can take it
and the atmos casino the most refined
casinos the buddha would say
is the one of consciousness which is the
ultimate peripheral of the
negative presence of negative yeah yeah
so there's nothing substantial to
consciousness but even that can be discerned by the
but even that can be discerned by the
the mind that has developed to such an
extent of that peripheral perception so to
of that peripheral perception so to
speak
but it's the same beginning that the
context that we talk about peripherally
that's the direction of any samadhi any
jhana any mind development any casino
any mind development any casino
establishment
and that's why if you cultivate it you
abandon anything inferior
that your mind would be focusing on and
picking on and nothing inferior can
bother you
and if you want to actually maybe here's
an example that can illustrate this
think about this you live in the village
or the city and you have your day-to-day
worries and happiness
and so on that's your life revolves
around it you don't really see the
greater totality
and suddenly you find out
on the news there is a massive comet
heading and it's gonna
there's a good chance it might wipe the
entire planet earth
the greater totality than the one you
live in specifically where you're
focusing in attending and choosing
how quickly would all of your village
warriors disappear
and got replaced by a greater world of
earth like i can this or this but if
earth goes and either of this will stay
the totality and that's exactly the
practice you want to upgrade your totality not
you want to upgrade your totality not
through focusing and staring at
various things that you might believe
represent on by actually contemplating
and discerning it as already there
the totality of experience in the
village or city or
home or lay life or whatever else is
within the totality of an enduring earth
the totality of an enduring earth
already
so what if i were to scare you on
account of that totality or everything
inferior would stop bothering you
because you get replaced by that father
but what if you were to then
overcome the fear in regard to the
totality of earth
how could you then possibly be afraid on
account of anything
that comes from the village because you
don't even care what happens to the
earth if that comet hits it or not you're
if that comet hits it or not you're
equanimous on that level
nothing inferior that comes to your
senses can bother you anymore
you have surmounted it and that's what
would have said even a petunia can
discern these totalities and use them to
abandon centrality and so on
what they cannot see without a right
view is how to relate rightly to that
is how to relate rightly to that
totality that is useful to abandon
that's like sometimes when people even
like you know like they have a notion of god
you know like they have a notion of god
or a divine and they use it to transcend
this world
you know the sensuality and everything
else because but
the relationship between them and the
totality of god or whatever they call it
that's has no understanding that's why
they're still protruding still liable to
rebirth and everything else
but then the buddha said but the target
that teaches not just the totality that
you can find
and use to abandon inferior things they
might bother you as in upgrade your
context even as a lay person it's not interested
even as a lay person it's not interested
in practice you'll be more beneficial to
upgrade your content and not just be
absorbed and narrow down to what's right
in front of you
find a greater totality and maintain
your mind on it um
but the target that teaches then
the understanding the gratification in
regards to the totality
the danger the escape basically
the buddha used the same description as
he used for like abandoning sensuality
and other wholesome states
how to abandon the casinos and that's
what differentiated him said
like a a man might establish himself
upon the
element of earth and because of that he
would abandon everything inferior to
that because he cultivates his mind on that
because he cultivates his mind on that
level that's a good cultivation
not necessarily wisdom of the right view
but obviously he is abandoning lots of
dust so if he were to hear the buddha's
teaching he wouldn't need much of an instruction
he wouldn't need much of an instruction
and that teaching would be
now the way you abandon everything
inferior understood it as impermanent
unsatisfactory turn the same reflection to that earth
turn the same reflection to that earth
because of which you abandoned
everything inferior
to that totality of earth remove your
emotional connection to the
i need this earth in order to be alive
become equanimous on that level
and then you would have understood the
extent of the gratification in earth
the danger in earth the escape in earth
and the path that leads
the way to escape the earth and then he
goes on to describe
the same principle for all the ten
casinos so it doesn't matter
how peripherally your mind can like is
developed or can develop
what matters is to keep basically
rehearsing and drilling the same
principle disintegrated totality develop a greater
disintegrated totality develop a greater
context
like even even more nusati in a way
mindfulness of death has a unifying
totality to everything you experience in
this life
it's basically practice of casino even
if it's not specifically
the topic of the of the casino
so if you if you were to take up a
context cultivate it
and then that context in itself see it
as a risen
against your will not in your control
you have no say in it if it comes or
goes or disappears
so you use it to abandon your attachment
and your infatuation with objects of
your senses
concerns of your senses you know one of
the prerequisites for anthony janna is
basically abandoning concern
and worry in regard to the world
in regards to basically the sense
objects you need to have been withdrawn
first sufficiently enough long enough and then
sufficiently enough long enough and then
the mind will start discerning these
this great totality so
ghana is another form of totality
practice like your mind establishes upon
greater totality
that in itself is free from greed
aversion delusion and it's wholesome
and that's why putin can attain germans
as well without the right view you don't
need the right view
to establish your mind in that principle
of that totality
but you need the form of establishment
of your mind in the principle of
totality in order to get the right view
in order to get the right view
now some people will need more of it
some people need lesser depending on how
you know quick and and and well-versed
your mind is
but nevertheless some form of samadhi in
that sense is needed like chitta samadhi
uh chittanimata is already a form of
it's a precursor to somebody it's
already form of somebody from portugal's
point of view composing a greater
context exactly so that's another totality
exactly so that's another totality
presence of the mind
the mood is always there regardless of
how you specifically feel or what you're
specifically doing or what you might be
doing what you're worried what you want to do
what you're worried what you want to do
there is a certain container of the moon
always enduring
so you recognize doesn't matter if the
mood is good or bad
or neutral the weight of the mood is
there that becomes your totality that becomes
that becomes your totality that becomes
your context
then now you're maintaining and by
maintaining the clarity in regard to it
you're basically
discerning the characteristics of that
mood oh it endures
again like there's nothing you're not
doing it you're not maintaining it
you're liable to it in the same sense
the weather endures
it affects the directions and so on but
neither of that
needs to be the basis for you being
affected the burden by it
the only time your burden body is when
your mind falls from that totality
and gets absorbed into things that are
being pressured by the mood for example
so element of earth means the element
the element of solid the greater
totality that partakes in
doesn't matter how specific and
particular things are or how general
they are
the earth is there enduring as a
necessary basis
the consciousness is there enduring as a
practically speaking the feeling is
there enduring as a necessary basis
that's when other students that would
have said feeling is the point of
converging the experience converges on feeling so
the experience converges on feeling so
feeling is a basis for convergence of
any kind
it's framework when we spoke about in
other talks we're establishing a minor
upon the creative framework
totality greater context is the same
principle so then when you hear about casinos or
so then when you hear about casinos or
something you approach it as another
oh another thing i focus on a clay pot
or a thing filled with water or a candle
flame and you see how far removed that is from
and you see how far removed that is from
the actual direction where casinos are
so it will become mystified because it's
fundamentally abstract because people
cannot relate to it
there's no basis for relating to it or
getting the right idea
but if you were to cultivate the general
context the peripheral context
in regard to your current experience and
always keep that peripheral eye
upon yourself even when you are focusing
on things
that's already closer to what the actual
casinos are even if you don't
specifically think
in terms of casinos
and like that's that's already the
nature of nimita nature of the sign
signs and tokens of things that even if
you see a sign stop
the command to stop to stop moving about
to not cross this line
is not in the sign the sign is literally
a shape red and white text that's what
you're perceiving
yet you are seeing the meaning behind
so that's what i mean even when people
are doing the focusing practices and so
on
you still cannot escape the meaning you
can only make yourself keep yourself
oblivious to it
even when you're staring at things your
thoughts are there giving the
significance of that you're just not
seeing it
because you think you're staring or
focusing you're somehow going to have a
magical release
but that's what limiter is already the
meaning behind things that you perceive
significant signs and tokens the
significances and when the buddha gave
the simile of nemita was like the cook
the two cooks they cook for a king and
one cooks
various dishes and pays no attention to
basically kind of preferences
that king will exhibit through his
behavior he will not
say i like this i don't like this but he
will take six scoops of this
and only one of this thus you refer
you descend a sign based on what you
perceived of taking this not taking this as
of taking this not taking this as
meaning he likes that
the sign that king likes that and then
the other
doesn't discern that well the one that
doesn't descend those signs gets fired
the one that discerns it he gets
promoted and it's the same the monk who
descends the signs of his own mind in
when he attends to this what signs
manifest what meaning is shown what arises his
what meaning is shown what arises his
essentiality non-sensuality
is it ill-will or non-ill will if he
pays no attention to what's behind
he will not progress in the dumb but
even that see
it's abstract for many people you say
nimita and they think these
glowing lights and flowering limited
signs and
projections and so on no it's literally
signs and tokens of things
the limit of the recorder the limit of
the book the limit of the robe what it
means what it represents what it stands
of
all the forms of limitations and yes you
look at the
objects that are agreeable to the eye
there are limiters
meaning of it that are basically
enticing pulling you towards sensuality but
pulling you towards sensuality but
you could also discern why the limiters
why the significance is that require a
bit more effort to establish
that the danger peril entrapment all of
the unwholesome
in the same thing you're perceiving does
the buddha say
the monk who wants to practice
mindfulness he doesn't attend
to the limiters of enticing nature he
attends to the
limiters they will result in this
passion
and those are not these things that are
kind of perceived
in the beautiful remains beautiful
you're still seeing the same beautiful
thing limiters are not in it
limiters are not in it
so that's already that's really like i'm
talking about is because that's already
the principle of that
of any mind development that includes
casino as well
the nimita the significance of of
certain necessary basis of solidity of
earth presence of element of earth if there
presence of element of earth if there
are no things in the world there will be
no perception in the world
so it doesn't matter how far that how
far it moved that might sound
abstractly it's still the most
like obvious fact even like if your body
is not there
as this sort of semi-solid lump
you would not be able to think perceive
feel like dislike be upset happy and so
on the necessity of physical body the
necessity of the element of earth
that's why often basically um
like rupa the word rupa was used for
form matter
of any kind and for the body because
that's your first point of
matter that you experience is your own
body any other matter you experience is
just basically experiencing the matter of
basically experiencing the matter of
your body that experience the matter
you you cannot perceive things with your
eyes you basically perceive your eyes
seeing things
but you see even on a day-to-day level
how much that's forgotten
lapsed from people's context you forget
that your senses are objects in the
world that you have no control over they
will wither and die
so you genuinely are fully absorbed in
the sense
objects fully repelled by them as if
there is no basis of your senses that
enables you for either of those
so it's already a form of totality
and actually yatana means that means
base means the extent
yeah fields as well sometimes was
translated so the practice of casino is the
so the practice of casino is the
practice of that peripheral
establishment upon
things that we unify both here and there
and my sense objects my sense organs and
my sense objects my sense organs and
science objects and everything in
between so whether i perceive this in in the
so whether i perceive this in in the
city we see that whether i'm happy on a
country but i perceive it here
or what i perceive over there if earth
is under threat
everything will be devalued because now
i have a greater border
that unifies includes me and the village
and the city
and the things that i like and things
that i dislike
now just abandon the war in regard but
don't abandon that peripheral context
that you do depend on the randomness of
the planet earth the winds that change
the earthquakes
all this all this and that's another
reflection that would have gave in
another certain way
so if this great earth these are
unchanging mountains and so on if they
are liable to change
which they are what is to be said about
this pathetic little body
and you experience this passion through
the recognition of
obvious nature that you've been ignoring
before because you haven't had a context
that even this great totality of earth
is liable to change in earthquakes and
shakes and this
disintegration and heat and so on
destruction basically
form deforms and i am based on it and
you are within that so if
form of that great kind great totality
deforms how can i have the slightest
notion that i want or i shouldn't
or i'll be affected when i do it's
ridiculous
and that's what would have said to those
monks like oh would you be upset if
people come and start breaking these
twigs and branches around us in this
woodland you say no because you know who gives
you say no because you know who gives
nobody nobody gives any
care about these things like that well
you so you should regard your own body
in the same sense like if it would be
broken destroyed
you should not be emotionally affected
because look
these mount himalayas are eroding and
what is to be said about this
soft little tiny
line for flesh like it's obvious
the only reason why it doesn't stick
with people is because they don't even
they don't invest enough effort to
maintain it on the level of the context
because it's pleasant yeah like let it
endure and protect it
it's it's more unpleasant see like it's
like like simmering fire that started
heating you up basically more and more
eventually the heat will accumulate
then you have that anxiety here what if
the element what if the earth what if
the world is to disappear yeah
it will you know what if it will
so you use that concern to become
economist in regard to that
concern on that level of the element of
earth planet of earth
and then nothing will bother you of the
inferior nature
but it's easier to seemingly easier
not in the long run but on the immediate
level it's easy to not look there and
not experience that anxiety
but instead choose to focus and absorb
and fully absorb yourself in the objects of
fully absorb yourself in the objects of
your senses
with the belief that that will somehow
reveal the great truth behind it that
will free you
so it's just basically you want more of
the sensuality pretty much because
that's what sensuality does
it's full absorption with a sense object
fully forgetting about the necessary
basis of your senses
the necessary basis of your enduring
pathetic little body
and all you see is the sense object and
you're fully kind of a passion with it
so now your meditation doesn't go to
those sense objects but takes another
sense objects of staring
hearing feeling touching touching
getting an image in the mind
getting images and visions in the minds
is like also it's the same thing
and you're pretty much expecting hoping
for the same results it will result in
the combination of the great pleasure of
enlightenment in nirvana
if you want to develop casinos start
developing peripheral awareness
mindfulness context
and clarity and you see
like the mind will then start being
established upon
the greater totality and you extend that
totality to the element of earth
element of cohesion element of heat
element of the presence
space element of space yeah consider
that light they would reveal any different
light they would reveal any different
colors doesn't matter
that's why like sari put in there oh no
maybe it was makamogalan actually
i can't remember one of the the top
monks at the time
it was the same log in front of him and
he was seeing it as earth
as water his fire as air right
the same thing it's beautiful it's
beautiful it's ugly it's
the same thing is this that's how versed
in all these extents he was he could
just pick them
he could just pick them peripherally in
regard to the same
attending log that he's attending to not
he's looking at different things and
forgetting about the lord
he's yeah he's basically cultivating the
discernment that he was
developing his mind yes discern the
element of cohesion that unifies
anything that appears in your experience
your feeling your thoughts perceptions
internally externally internally and externally